<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A short, yet a true and faithfull narration of the fearefull fire that fell in the towne of Wooburne, in the countie of Bedford, on Saturday the 13. of September last, Anno. 1595 Together with a Christian admonition as to the particular people of that place]</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13384</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1646:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A short, yet a true and faithfull narration of the fearefull fire that fell in the towne of Wooburne, in the countie of Bedford, on Saturday the 13. of September last, Anno. 1595 Together with a Christian admonition as to the particular people of that place]</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Widdow Orwin, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages torn, with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page lacking, supplied from Bodleian Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fires --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Woburn (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13384:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13384:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, AND HIS VERIE GOOD LL. SIR IOHN POPHAM Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England, and Sir</hi> William Periam Knight, Lord chiefe Baron of her Maiesties Court of Exchequer, T.W. hartily wiſheth the abundant riches of al Gods mercies in this life, &amp; eternal bleſsednes in that which is to come tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I doubt not (my good Lords) but that you haue ere this heard of the feareful and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table fire, that in September last light vpon the towne of VVoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne, in the countie of Bedford, and am fullie perſwaded, that according to the meaſure of heauenly wiſedome, that God hath vouchſaued to you both, you haue made ſpirituall profit, not only thereof, but of ſundry other ſuch like iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments paſt alreadie, in diuers quarters of our kingdom, and iuſtly feared, that hereafter may
<pb facs="tcp:13384:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13384:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13384:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13384:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13384:4"/>fall out vpon vs for our ſinnes: yet becauſe the particularities of that puniſhment are not ſo wel and certainly knowne as were meete, mens minds are ſo various, and fame increaſeth by going, as wee ſay in the Prouerbe, beſides that euen in theſe things, likewiſe there is a trueth fit to be vnderstood, &amp; alſo becauſe the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of men, either ſee them not, becauſe they are blind, or els bee amazed at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a while, becauſe they haue no further inſight, or elſe make not good vſe of them, becauſe they are of careleſſe hearts, I haue thought it ſit, and that vnder your Lordſhippes protections, and with your good acceptation alſo I trust, to publiſhe though a ſhort, yet a true narration of that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſpectacle, and therewithall, ſome medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mine owne concerning that matter begunne within a daye or two after the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named fire it ſelfe, and finiſhed in howe ſhort a ſpace I will not write, least I might ſeeme to vaunt. In regard of the matter, I haue aimed at nothing but this, that the trueth it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laide open, and ſome obſeruations made thereupon, men might bee lead by the hande to make ſome profitable vſe of it, they being drawne on to repentance for that which is paſt, and carefully to looke to themſelues for that
<pb facs="tcp:13384:4"/>which is to come, leaſt otherwiſe the flame of Gods wrath ſhould break forth further againſt vs, and that to our vtter waſting and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For the manner obſerued in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, it is not ſo methodicall I confeſſe, as it ſhould be: but the reaſon thereof was the ſodain feare and great griefe, that I conceiued vpon the very viewe and ſight of the ruines it had made, all making me vnfit indeed for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, eſpeciallie for matter or manner to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſuch a ſubiect, as it ought, both the one and the other then tooke ſuch a deepe impreſsion in me, and that is the reaſon alſo and nothing elſe I aſſure you, why I ſeeme as it were ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly to deale in the cauſe, for how can a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered mind be ſit, eſpecially in methode to propound any matter, ſith that to the orderlie deliuerie of thinges, there muſt of neceſsitie concurre a quiet hart, and a ſtaied head? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit this I dare notwithſtanding proteſt, that for the bodie of the treatie, there is in it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnſound or vncertaine, and therefore in that reſpect may the more ſafely be receiued. As for the reaſons leading me to preſent this little labour to your Lordſhips, though they bee many &amp; the ſame waightie alſo, yet take them I beſeech you, in a worde as it were. You haue
<pb facs="tcp:13384:5"/>vouchſaued me ſundry honorable fauours, and I would not willingly ſeeme or be thought, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnmindfull of them, or vnthankefull for them in any dutie that God hath or ſhalbe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to inable me to performe. You execute the iustice of the land, nay which is more, the verie iustice of God himſelfe, euen deriued from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by her Maieſties holy hand and power. How fit therefore it is, that his example ſhould bee ſet before you, whoſe perſon you doe in ſome ſort beare, and whoſe iudgement alſo you exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute in your functions, that ſo you might in your places tread alſo in ſome good meaſure in his pathes, your ſelues can more wiſely iudge, than I am able to relate. You both profeſſe the holy goſpell of Chriſt, and may in ſome ſort and ſenſe be reckoned amongst them, that mourne for your owne ſinnes, and for the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the land alſo. How meet it is, that you and others with you ſhuld ſee, that you haue not taken vp this lamentation without cauſe, as welfor that which is paſt &amp; preſent, as for that which is feared to come. But I will repreſſe my ſelfe in theſe thinges, and will not ceaſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all the graces that I haue receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, to comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theſe cauſes into his moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful hands, who only worketh wonderful things
<pb facs="tcp:13384:5"/>both in heauen and in earth, that ſo turning vs from our euil waies vnto himſelfe, and knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our harts daily more and more vnto him, wee may haue aſſured hope of the bettering of our estate in this life according to his owne good pleaſure, or at the leaſt of the euerlaſting ſauing of our ſoules, notwithstanding all the troubles and turmoiles that may fal out in the world. The Lord alwaies and in all things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo direct your Lorſhips both by his holy ſpirite, and vntill the daye of Chriſt make perfecte in you all good works that hee hath begun for the proſperitie of Sion, or the commoditie of the common wealth, to his glorie, and your euerlasting comforte thorowe Chriſt. London the <hi>1.</hi> of Nouember. <hi>1595.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips bounden and readie euer in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Tho. Wilcocks, <hi>the Lords vnworthie.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13384:6"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13384:6"/>
            <head>A ſhort narration of the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fire, that fell in the towne of <hi>VVooburne, in the Countie of Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, on Saturdaie, the</hi> 13. <hi>of September last.</hi> 1595. <hi>Lord Ieſus begin and make an ende.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EN, brethren and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea &amp; whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer amongſt you tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feareth God, vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly loueth his lawe, ſtedfaſtlye beleeueth his promiſes, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely obeieth his wil to you, and to euery one of you, I ſay, are the words of trueth, and exhortation following directed: not of a hatefull heart I aſſure you againſt any, for I wiſh &amp; would labour your good generally, and eſpecially the ſaluation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13384:7"/>of your ſoules, as mine owne: nor yet of a minde curious in other mens cauſes, with the neglect of them that belong to my ſelfe, for I know it to bee diſpleaſing before God, and vnprofitable to my ſelfe, but of an earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in chriſtian charitie, by al meanes lawful, and that according to my vttermoſt abilitie, to aſſay to doe good vnto others, as vnto mine owne ſoule, and to labour what I can, the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of his glory, that hath created vs and placed vs in this worlde, for that ſpeciall end and purpoſe, that ſo at the laſt alſo, after we haue a little glorified him here, we might thorough his mercie, and Chriſts merites, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the fruition of euerlaſting life, and the immortall glorification of our bodies and ſoules, in that great and laſt day. Wherein, if either thorow the vncleanenes of my heart, or the pollution of my hands, or thorow any other weakenes or want in mee, or of mee, I ſhall miſſe of my purpoſe: or elſe thorow the careleſneſſe, contempt, or any other corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beſides, of thoſe into whoſe hands this treatiſe ſhall come, theſe poore labors ſhal not ſort theſe deſired effects, I ſhall for mine own and their tranſgreſsions (which are lettes and hinderances to ſo worthie a worke) mourne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13384:7"/>in my ſoule in ſecret, to ſee or heare the hand of God come forth ſo heauilie againſt vs for our ſinnes, and yet I ſhall againe comfort my ſelfe, as well as I can, not onely in this of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men, that in great and hard matters to haue a will is ſufficient, but eſpecially in that heauenly ſpeech of the holy apoſtle, that God (if there be firſt a willing &amp; cheerefull mind) accepteth vs according to that wee haue, and not according to that we haue not: this being alwaies prouided alſo, that that good, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee of affection, or of action, that wee haue, we haue from him, who worketh in vs both the will and the deede, according to his own good pleaſure, and therefore will accept it in vs, as his own good worke, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our imperfections and defects cleauing thereto.</p>
            <p>What a fearefull fire fell in the towne of <hi>Wooburne,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Bedford,</hi> on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday, as they call it, the thirteenth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember laſt paſt, ſundrie of the people there felt, to their extreame loſſes, yea vtter vndoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diuers did behold to their great griefe, and many haue heard of, euen to the ſorrow of their hearts. This was ſo much the more lamentable, not onely becauſe it burnt vp ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13384:8"/>houſes, &amp; baies of building, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as I take it, of ſome hundred and thirtie, one with another ſuch as they were, of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling howſes, and out houſes, as barnes, ſtables, houels, and ſuch like, but alſo becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed whatſoeuer ſtore was laide vp in the ſame, as corne, hey, wood, ferne, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like prouiſion, for man and for beaſt, for the backe and the bellie, to bake and to brew with, and for ſuch other both neceſſarie vſe, and profitable maintenance: yea (which may adde to &amp; increaſe the pitifulnes of the ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle, and the very matter of the narration it ſelfe) not only many things within the houſe, being almoſt vtterly ſpoyled, broken to pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and conſumed, as tables, ſtooles, bedſteds, wainſcot, preſſes, glaſſe in the windowes, pewter, braſſe, copper, leather, and ſuch like, but euen of that which was caried into the ſtreetes to ſaue it, if it might be, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the force of the fire, as linnen, bedding, platters, diſhes, kettles, much ſtolen away, and ſundrie ſortes of ware, of the traders of the towne, as friſe, durance, ſheewes, and ſuch like, purloyned &amp; imbeſeled. By meanes whereof it commeth to paſſe, that the moſt of them are greatlie weakened, as in reſpect of that poore eſtate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13384:8"/>worldly, which before they enioyed, yea that diuers of them hauing their ſtore and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion conſumed, and as it were eaten vp with the flame of the fire, hardly haue for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, their wiues, children, and ſeruants, breade to ſlake hunger, drinke to coole thirſt, wood to warme them with all, or houſes to hide their heads in, I will not ſay conuenient (for that were a great mercie in this iudgement) but not ſuch as ouer head, are able to keepe out the raine, ſnow, and other moyſture that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, or on the ſides to beate backe the boyſterous windes, and cold ayre, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede being rather wrought, by the indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or rage of ſome, that came in to ſuccor and helpe their diſtreſſe, by burſting in peeces the tiles of the houſe, and breaking downe walles, windowes, glaſſe, and all (and yet no doubt of it, ment to doe their beſt indeuours, for ayde and reliefe) than by the violence or vehemencie of the fire.</p>
            <p>Many I doubt not, are greatly egar, and greedie as it were, to heare of, and to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meane whereby this miſerable fire, and fearefull flame was inkindled: which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of theirs, as I cannot miſlike, if it bee free from new fanglednes and curioſitie, and haue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13384:9"/>this adioyned there withall, that they labour what they can, to make a good and profitable vſe of the ſame: ſo will I to my vttermoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, though not in all and euery particular, yet in truth and plainenes, aſſay to ſatisfie, and certifie them thereof. A ſimple old woman, as ſimple and ſeelie, as euer I knew almoſt, ſlow in ſpeech, deafe in hearing, and which is worſt of all, very dull of vnderſtanding and ſenſe (named for her age, olde <hi>Ioane</hi>) dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a poore cottage, at the further ende of the towne, towards <hi>Brickhill,</hi> hauing ſhifted her bed ſtrawe, and put new thereinto, laide the olde in the chimney of her ſaide houſe, ſuppoſing in deede, as ſhe affirmeth, that there had bin no fire in the ſame. Afterwards go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad, about ſome buſineſſes that ſhe had to doe, though verilie they were but meane and ſmall (as ſuch poore folkes haue no great affayres) the cinders and ſparkes that were in the ſame chimney, tooke hold of that ſtraw, ſo careleſly caſt thereinto, and inflamed, and by meanes thereof ſet on fire that thatched houſe, and in very ſhort time tooke holde of others adioyning vnto it, that were thatched alſo, and ſo proceeded in fearefull both mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and manner, from one to another, till it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13384:9"/>had made that lamentable deſolation, that is yet to bee ſeene. And as this was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this wofull worke, ſo was it without al doubt very much furthered, by the abſence of ſundry the inhabitants of that towne, who being at that time far from home, and abroad in the fieldes about their worldly affayres, could neither ſo prouidently preuent the rage of that fire, nor ſo powerfullie put it out, as by all probabilitie they might haue done, had they been at the very beginning thereof. Beſides this is moſt certaine, that the Lord rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp euen almoſt at that very inſtant, a great and mightie wind, to carrie it as it were from one houſe or place to another (the fire alſo it ſelfe, naturally gathering winde vnto it) (as to mee was tolde) was euen made thereby the more forcible and furious, whilſt all things, that either they had for defence, or had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in for prouiſion, were ſo far off from leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the furie of the fire, that they did rather increaſe the ſame. For beſides, that the thatch of their barnes and out houſes, was greatly dried with much and long parching heate and drouth going before, &amp; ſo they were the more meete matter, for the flame to ſet vpon, beſides this I ſay, their corne, their hay, their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13384:10"/>wood, their ferne, and other prouiſion laide thereinto, and being very drily inned, as they vſe to ſaye, was fit foode for the fire to feede vpon, not onely for the increaſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame heate, and violent rage of the fire it ſelfe, but euen to the turning and burning of the matter it ſelfe into duſt and powder. And not onely the ſodaine, but the great puffes and blaſtes of the ſaide winde alſo, did carrie ſparkes &amp; flames from one houſe to another, yea (which is more ſtrange) from the one ſide of the towne to the other: this being by the faithfull teſtimonie of ſundry credible perſons, not onely eare, but eye witneſſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, truely reported, that there was by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and vehemency of the ſame winde ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, from one of the houſes ſo conſumed, and ſtanding not farre from the Church, a flake of thatch inflamed, as broad as it were a ſheete, and caried quite and cleane ouer the Chauncell of the Church, the ſchoolehouſe, and ſome other houſing of the weſt ſide of the towne, and fell vpon ſome of the houſing of the eaſt ſide of the ſaid towne, where alſo it burned ſome fifteene or ſixteene baye of building as I take it. To all this we may adde, as meanes to increaſe this inkindled flame,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13384:10"/>the carefulnes of the people, come together out of the fieldes, and their careleſnes alſo. If any man thinke it ſtrange, that ſuch contraries ſhould either be in one and the ſelfe ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, or further one and the ſelfe ſame action, let him weigh, that the care that they had, to carrie ſome of their goods out of their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes, into the ſtreetes and other places, leaſt the fire alſo ſhould haue taken hold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, made them careleſſe to ſtop the paſſage of the fire, which driuen as I ſay, by the force of the wind, did not only paſſe ſpeedily from one place to another, but made as it were a glade from the end of the town, on the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of it eſpecially, euen to the Churche or temple yet ſtanding there (thanks be to God) not much decayed or defaced, to the end the people might more diligently reſorte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire thereto, and more fruitfully profite by the heauenly exerciſes there performed, than ther haue done, or elſe God will proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea more fiercely againſt it, the towne and all. And which is not of leaſt conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce concerning this cauſe: Though the people of the countrey came in very louingly and readily, (many of them leauing their owne labours, and freeing their hired workemen
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13384:11"/>from their taske, and paying them notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their daies wages) to helpe to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and quench the fire, and indeed though diuers of them wrought and toiled very ſore and hard there about: yet ſome thorow want of experience, in ſuch particular actions and cauſes, and other ſome for lacke of good gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (a ſpecial remedie doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in ſuch extreame and dangerous cauſes) tooke not the readieſt and eaſieſt way to ſtop or hinder the paſſage of this fearefull flame, but being as commonly people are, in other caſes of greater quiet, and therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in this hurly burlie, of many mindes, what thorowe ignorance and ſtrangenes of the ſight, and want of experience in ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſuall actions, confounded in themſelues, cried ſome one thing and ſome another, and indeede did ſome one thing and ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all ſuppoſing they ſaide and did for the beſt, but indeed, though not of purpoſe (for I dare not ſo much as thinke that any caried ſuch bad minds) increaſed rather the deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and waſt, than any manner of way leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame.</p>
            <p>In all this lamentable diſcourſe or narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there are ſurely many points worthy the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13384:11"/>obſeruation and marking: all and euerie one whereof directly tende to the manifeſtation of moſt excellent things in God himſelfe, for example, his great power, his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, his perfect iuſtice, his heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and mercie more than fatherly, yea more than can be ſpoken or thought of: and to the declaration of many foule and feareful corruptions, that lie lurking in vs, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerue for our Chriſtian admonition and inſtruction, as well for that which is paſt and preſent, as alſo for all time hereafter to come, ſpecially if wee haue eies to ſee the wayes of God in his works, or hearts to tremble at his iudgements, or mindes that can bee affected with his fauours, or any grace and abilitie to make good vſe either of the one, or of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For tell me I pray you firſt, was not this a plaine proofe of his power, vpon ſo ſmall beginnings to make ſo great a flame, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire? to execute his iudgement by ſo weake inſtruments and meanes? to raiſe vp the creatures for the further diſperſing of the iudgement? to accompliſh his owne purpoſe and counſell, in ſo ſhort a ſeaſon, and ſmall a time? to ſtrike ſuch feare and amazednes into the mindes, not onely of weake women and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13384:12"/>little children, but of men (who ſeeme to haue more courage and wiſdome) that their heads ſhould not be able to deuiſe what were moſt profitable, nor their hands fit to execute anie thing to ſpeake of in compariſon? If any and euery one of theſe be euident declarations of his might and maieſtie, what then are al theſe together, but ſtrong inſtruments more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to perſwade our hearts in his all-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and almightie power? And dooth not this ſhew his wonderfull prouidence, that he did not onely beare the perſons of all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them, as it were vpon the wings of his gracious goodnes, ſo as wee may by a manner of ſpeech ſaye, and confeſſe it to the glory of his name, and the ſtrengthening of our perſwaſion in trouble againſt time to come, that not one of them did ſo much as daſh his foot againſt a ſtone, but ſpared much of that, that the fire had, as wee may ſay, laid handes on, and the flame no doubt, woulde haue conſumed that, that it had fearefully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of, had not he reſtrained it, and kept it as it were in his fiſt? Doth not this argue hisiuſtice, in ſtriking for ſinne? he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Gods nature will eaſily giue glory to God in it, and confeſſe the truth. For we know by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13384:12"/>the trueth of the worde, and our experience and obſeruation in the world, that he deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not in puniſhing the ſonnes of men, and if their tranſgreſsions were not as it were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ropes to hale downe iudgements, ſurelie men ſhould neuer taſte of this, howſoeuer it might be alwayes in the diuine nature. Nay I will ſay more. May wee not as well in the maner of the iudgement, as in the iudgement it ſelfe, yea in the very things ſtriken with his wrath, beholde the haude of God puniſhing the ſinnes of men, in thoſe members and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, they had moſt abuſed to licenciouſneſſe and euill. Yea to ſpeake more plainely of this particular, was it not a token of wrath from aboue, by fire to conſume their bread, meate, and ſtrong drinke, that they had prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the faire, thereby to put them in mind how they haue offended, yea doe offend (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this chaſtiſement and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in abuſing theſe bleſsings to gourman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and drunkennes? And doth not this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his wiſedome, that in that outwarde iudgement he hath ſcourged, as ſundry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and careleſſe men, ſo ſome alſo that in ſome meaſure, do vnfainedly feare his name, heartily loue his trueth, and carefully walke
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13384:13"/>in obedience of his will? And why hath hee done it? Surely that in both ſorts, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and al men might ſee, that if God, as in reſpect of outward puniſhment, ſpare not his owne people (who are as deare to him as the apple of his eye) he will much leſſe in this, or that which is to come, winke at the ſinnes of the wicked, (for if iudgement beginne at the houſe of God, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, what ſhall be the end of them that obey not the goſpell of God?) and that his ſeruants might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that therefore they are chaſtened of the Lord in this life, to the end that the droſſe of their corruption being ſcoured from them, they ſhoulde not periſhe with this wicked world. And as for his mercie, what can wee caſt our eie vpon (I will not ſay, if wee looke vpon it with ſanctified and inlightned minds from aboue, but euen in the light of reaſon or nature) and that in this very deſolation it ſelf? or thinke vpon with our mindes, in which we may not ſee the glory of it breake forth as the ſunne in his greateſt brightnes? For if the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> for himſelfe and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, did frankly confeſſe it, as he doth indeed, Lament. 3. that it was the Lords mercie that they were not conſumed: And the faithfull
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13384:13"/>in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> willingly acknowledge, that vnles the Lord of hoſts had reſerued ſome, though but few, they had beene as Sodom, and made like vnto Gomorrah? Haue not wee as good cauſe, with vnfained minds and mouths, alſo to ſpeak and declare the ſame? More than the one halfe of the towne, by much, was neither touched by fire (howſoeuer it was threatned therewith) nor receiued any great loſſe: and yet I hope they thinke not themſelues more righteous than the reſt, ſure I am they ſhould not imagine any ſuch thing, for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt them that felt not the flame, I am ſure there were as great tranſgreſſors, as they that taſted of it. And as for them vpon whom the loſſe did light, and indeede lieth very heauilie, a great part of their dwelling houſes, I confeſſe was ſore ſet vpon &amp; aſſaulted, yea very much ſcorched with fire, but yet not deſtroyed: much alſo of their goods or houſholde ſtuffe graciouſly ſpared, though greatly defaced &amp; impaired. And which is a very rare &amp; ſtrange thing, ſpecially in ſo exemplary a iudgment, none of them or theirs, in their bodies or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, hurt with this fearful flame. Nay which is more: of all that confuſed multitude that was there for needful help and ſuccour, ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13384:14"/>running one way and ſome another, ſome crying one thing, and ſome another, ſome doing this, and ſome that, and all as if it were a beaſt of many heads for the time, by reaſon they were without good guides or gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not one of them all I ſaye, for ought I heard, maymed or hurt. Surely, if a better eie had not watched ouer them than humane, and a more not onely mightie, but gracious hand vphelde them, than their owne, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to one as wee ſay in our prouerbe, but that in climing of houſes, beating downe of tiles, occupying of axes, caſting of water, (all which and many the like are vſed in ſuch fearefull extremities) euery one beſides run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thicke and threefold in anothers necke, but that diuers had beene wounded, if not ſlaine. And yet to the end we might behold, euen as it were with our bodily eyes, as well as with the eies of our minde, Gods great and gracious goodnes, not one of ſo many did miſcarrie, or was as we may ſay, ſcarſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at all, with any dangers either deadly or grieuous. What ſhall we ſay then? without all controuerſie, he that cannot learne by that which is paſt, to feare and tremble before God in ſo fearefull a iudgement, muſt needes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13384:14"/>be deemed to haue at the leaſt, a careleſſe hart, if not benummed and ſenſeleſſe. For ſhall the Lion roare, and not all the beaſtes of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt feare? And he that cannot bee thankfull for the gracious reſeruation, that God of his meere mercie hath made both of men, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, goods, &amp;c. and that as well for other mens as for his owne, may iuſtly bee ſaid to bee of an vnthankfull minde and mouth to Godwarde, and of an vncharitable heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his brethren. And whoſoeuer cannot vſe it to further him in faith vnfained, and ſincere repentance, as in regard of the former part of his life miſpent, and for carefulneſſe &amp; circumſpection for that which is to come, let him doubt at the leaſt if not deſpaire of his preſent and ſubſequent condition. For if God ſhall giue vs ſo liuely documentes as theſe are, and wee not receiue inſtruction thereby, or bee in ſome good meaſure bettered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, both for knowledge, beliefe, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, hee ſhall haue iuſt occaſion to take vp that grieuous complaint againſt vs, which he hath done to men of like qualitie and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and to ſay, <hi>Hearken O heauens, &amp; thou O earth, heare, for the Lord ſpeaketh: I haue brought vp children, yea I haue exalted them,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13384:15"/>but falling away they haue rebelled againſt me. The oxe knoweth his owner, and the aſſe his Maſters cribbe, but Iſraell knoweth not, my people conſider not. Ah ſinfull nation, ah peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden with iniquitie, a very wicked ſeede, corrupted children: they haue forſaken the Lorde, they haue contemptuouſly prouoked the holy one of Iſraell: wherefore ſhould ye be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any more, ſith you increaſe your falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: the whole head is dangerouſlie ſicke, and the whole heart languiſheth, from the ſole of the foote to the toppe of the head, there is no ſoundnes, but wounds and ſwellings, and a ſore that runneth continuallie, &amp;c.</hi> which miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſchiefes, and grieuous inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that we may thorow Gods goodnes ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily auoide, as alſo by the ſame aſſuredly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the contrary good thinges: it ſhall bee good for vs to marke, firſt the hand that ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs, leſt otherwiſe not knowing that, we runne whither wee ſhould not, and forſake that we ought to cleaue vnto. Secondly, the cauſes mouing ſuch exemplary iudgement, becauſe the ignorance thereof may make vs to lay it where wee ſhould not, and to cleere them that wee ought to charge. And laſtly, the endes that are aimed at in theſe chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13384:15"/>becauſe as we are not afflicted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, ſo we are not chaſtiſed but to ſome good and holy purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Hee that thus correcteth men, is euen the eternall God himſelfe, as we may well ſee, not only by this generall ſentence of the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Is there any euill in the citie that the Lord hath not done?</hi> chap. 3. meaning by the terme <hi>euill,</hi> the euill of puniſhment and affliction, and not the euill of ſinne and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion, becauſe God cannot that way (hee is ſo abſolutely good) be an actor at al: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the particular confeſsion, that <hi>Iob</hi> the holy man of God maketh, when hee ſaith, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the greateſt iudgements almoſt, that can fall out vpon men in this life: <hi>The Lorde hath giuen, the Lord hath taken away, bleſsed be the name of the Lord.</hi> And as Gods word doth almoſt euery where in plaine and audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble termes affirme the ſame, ſaying, <hi>The Lord doth whatſoeuer pleaſeth him, both in heauen, and in earth, and in all deepe places:</hi> ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon grounded vpon religion confirmeth it likewiſe. For if this be not ſo, why doe we ſay we beleeue with our hearts, and confeſſe with our mouthes that God is almightie? Is it not becauſe wee are certainly perſwaded
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13384:16"/>both by the will of GOD reuealed in his worde, and by his workes manifeſted in the world, that no ſuch things as theſe, are or can bee performed, but by not onely his permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and prouidence (which indeed reach not vnto the actions of God, otherwiſe than as he ſuffereth and foreſeeth the ſame, but to his determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, councell, foreſight, or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) but by his al-ſufficient might and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer alſo, at all times, in all places, and in all thinges, ruling, yea ouerruling the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good pleaſure of his owne will: which if it were not true, we ſhould in our profeſsion of it, haue been found falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiers of trueth, and in our perſwaſions of it, deceiuers of our owne hearts. Neither doth this hinder it (howſoeuer in humane reaſon it may ſeeme ſo) that in the execution of his councels, he vſeth means. For as we are ſure, that with meanes, and without meanes, yea and againſt meanes too, hee can performe whatſoeuer he will, either as in regard of the grieuous puniſhment of the wicked, or as in reſpect of the mercifull deliuerance of his owne people (which we may plainly and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſee, in the paſſage of the Iſraelites thorow the red ſea, that not only giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13384:16"/>way, but being as a wal for them on the right hand, and on the left, and ſeruing of or the drowning of the Egyptians therein) ſo hee both appoynteth and vſeth the meanes, not for any impotencie, or weaknes in himſelfe, for hee is the God of all might and power, communicating it in great meaſure to many, and yet hauing neuer a whit the leſſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and brideling that that hee hath giuen them, making their rage alſo to turne to his praiſe, but that he might the more effectually humble, who being groſſe of nature, are hardly brought vnder, or made to ſtoope, but by ſuch apparant and forcible meanes. And this may appeare, not onely then when he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth groſſe and outward meanes (and yet the ſame powerfull alſo) becauſe they better ſort with our nature, &amp; more liuely affect all our ſenſes, but euen then when hee maketh the weakeſt, and the meaneſt able to effect moſt great and excellent matters. And therfore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les we be in ſinne hardned as flints, theſe and ſuch like things, cannot chuſe, but pinch and pearce vs very farre. To apply all this to our particular, as purpoſe, ſo paſt, yea and if you will preſent viſitation alſo: which howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as in regard of time it be paſt alreadie, yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13384:17"/>are the monuments, &amp; the very cinders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo preſent before vs, that all our ſenſes, ſight, hearing, feeling, ſmelling, taſting, may ſtill, yea and I feare me will a long while bee ſatisfied therewith. Wherein though the Lord vſed the careleſnes and negligence of a ſillie poore wretched woman, for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this puniſhment, as you haue heard alreadie; and though for the continuance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and carrying of it, yea ſcattering of it abroad, he raiſed vp a mightie wind, &amp; other inſtruments and meanes aboue expreſſed, to ſerue his own turne with, for the declaration of his maieſtie, and the chaſtiſements of the ſinnes of the people: yet ſtill if wee haue any grace, we muſt ſtedfaſtly looke vpon him, &amp; vnfeignedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that he as it were alone, hath wrought this great worke. And the knowledge and practiſe of this poynt dooth holy <hi>Iob</hi> teach vs, and that not onely in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the like nature and euent, but in ſuch plaine termes alſo, as wil admit or receiue no other conſtruction. For howſoeuer he was not ignorant of, yea by the credible report of his eſcaped ſeruants, he knewe well enough, and was perſwaded, that the Caldeans, Sabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Satan and al, had as it were conſpired and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13384:17"/>conſented, but yet euerie one, in and about the thinges wherein they were imployed, as for example, in driuing away his cattle, as it had beene a praye or ſpoyle obtained in iuſt warre, in the ouerthrowing of that houſe wherein his children were banquetting, and in the reſt of the miſeries and afflictions that God was pleaſed to exerciſe him withall, yet doth he from the hart, frankly and freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and ſay, <hi>The Lord hath giuen, the Lorde hath taken away:</hi> And to his diſcomfortable and wicked wife affirme, <hi>Shall wee receiue good at the hand of God, and not receiue euill alſo?</hi> And indeed if we be not thorowly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of this in our hearts, as by the cleere light of the worde, ſo by the gracious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gods bleſſed ſpirite in our ſeuerall ſoules, we ſhall with the blind and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the world, irreligiouſly aſcribe as they doe, the matters and occurences that fall out in this life, to fortune and ſecondary cauſes, which is nothing elſe in trueth, but to ſpoyle and robbe the diuine maieſtie of his power, prouidence, wiſedome, iuſtice, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer therein is moſt excellent. And if we doe not with a ſound mind and mouth, giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God therin, and confeſſe it to the praiſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13384:18"/>of his name, ſurely it is impoſsible, either to miniſter ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to others that are di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, a dutie that in charitie we are bound to performe towardes men, or with patience and comfort to vndergoe our owne calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and miſeries, a cauſe that we ought great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to care for, or quietly and confidently to expect a ioyfull iſſue of them and way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape therefrom, a matter that we muſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently hope for, or elſe all will bee nought on our ſides. For howe is it likely that a man ſhould quietly indure the croſſes and loſſes that fall vpon him, who knoweth not that they are inflicted, not onely by a ſuperior, but by an abſolute ouerruling power, and the ſame not vſurped, but moſt holie, lawfull, &amp; iuſt? or howe can hee ſo much as thinke of a comfortable deliuerance, that is not well and thorowly perſwaded of the almightie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and prouidence of God, who if he worke it not for him, it can neuer be effected? And if hee cannot as a skilfull Phiſitian, heale the maladies and ſickneſſes of his owne ſoule, and miniſter conſolation to his owne conſcience, how ſhall wee imagine him able to doe it to others? For as for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s miſchieuons minds (if our croſſes and calamities come altogether
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13384:18"/>from them) they cannot be ſatisfied, till wee bee ruinated and ouerthrowne: and Satans malice ſpecially againſt Gods people, hath nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther end nor meaſure, if it bee not reſtrained. This perſwaſion therefore, that we are vnder Gods almightie hand and power, in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſtate or condition we be, being well ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in our hearts, will vndoubtedly cauſe vs, that in the time of our proſperitie, wee ſhall not be puffed vp in pride aboue meaſure, and in the daies of our aduerſitie, not to bee too much depreſſed, but euen for the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent patiently to beare, and for the time to come, with comfort to expect and waite for ſuch a deliuery and iſſue out of all troubles, as the Lord ſhall ſee to be fit for the glory of his name, the benefit of his people, and our own euerlaſting good. Whereas without this, we ſhal either with ſome of the wicked languiſh away in diſtruſtfulneſſe; murmuring, and all manner of impatiencie, or with other ſome fall to vngodly deuiſes and ſhiftes, imagining either to haue our neceſsities ſatisfied by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, fraud, force, theft, or ſome ſuch like wicked way, or elſe that our griefes may and ſhall bee recouered by repayring to witches, ſorcerers, coniurers, and ſundry other ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13384:19"/>wicked perſons, the practiſe wherof we may beholde to too many in our time ouertaken withall, and running ryot to that great and grieuous exceſſe of euill. Wherefore wee may well ſee and ſay, that it much ſtandeth vs in hand indeed, yea and greatly importeth all and euery one of vs, to bee rightly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perſwaded, as of other grounds &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian religion, ſo of this one point particularly, and that not onely for the auoyding of iniquitie and ſinne, in louing &amp; liking, in ſeeking and ſtriuing to them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their groſſe and grieuous tranſgreſsions, we ought to loath and abhorre, but euen for the faithfull accompliſhment of many good duties in pietie towardes God, in charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, and in comfort and patience, as in reſpect of ourſelues. For otherwiſe, how ſhall wee ſtedfaſtly truſt in, or religiouſly call vpon him, whome wee beleeue not to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie? or how can wee comfort our ſelues or other men, if there bee any power that is either equall with, or can ouerrule the ſame?</p>
            <p>Nowe wee are to ſee what cauſes ſhould moue the Lord, in ſuch fearefull meaſure and manner, as many times he doth, to exerciſe &amp;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13384:19"/>execute his iudgements. Of a truth it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not of himſelfe, and his owne nature, as though hee tooke pleaſure in puniſhing the ſonnes of men. For the ſcripture telleth vs in many places, that hee is as it were of another diſpoſition, namely, ſlow to wrath, &amp; of great goodnes, and inclinable to much mercie, (for which purpoſe ſee Exod. 34. and Pſalm. 86.) neither indeede delighteth hee to afflict his owne creatures, ſpecially man the excellenteſt and chiefeſt of the reſt. Some thing then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> elſewhere, muſt of neceſsitie draw him and driue him to doe it, or elſe it could neuer bee performed From our ſelues therefore ſurely, and our moſt grieuous tranſgreſsions, is the firſt, yea and as a man may ſay, indeede is the onely cauſe of all our miſerie, of what kinde, ſorte, or condition ſoeuer it bee, either out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in the bodie, or inwarde in the minde, temporall in this life, or euerlaſting in that which is to come. Which becauſe men are not eaſily perſwaded of, nor willingly yeelde to (pride and conceitednes concerning ſome good things in themſelues, taketh ſo ſtrong hold of them, and poſſeſſeth them ſo mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) God in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry places of the holy ſcripture, doth not onely plainely deſcribe the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13384:20"/>of mans nature, ſaying, <hi>The thoughts and imaginations of mans heart are onely euill, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day from his youth vpwarde:</hi> and againe, <hi>There is none that doth good, no not one, they are al become corrupt &amp; abominal le, &amp;c.</hi> But alſo by his Prophet peremptorily telleth vs, <hi>that our ſins are they that make a ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and vs:</hi> and againe in another place, <hi>Thy deſtruction O Iſraell is of thy ſelfe.</hi> For the further cleering and confirmation of which point, we are to marke that God at the firſt made man, iuſt, holy, innocent, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp;c. but he not continuing in that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent eſtate, corrupted himſelfe and all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, who as they were by creation in his loynes, ſo were they all ſtanding with him in innocencie, had hee ſtoode, and falling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him thorow tranſgreſsion. So that nowe it is no more naturall for man, as man, that is to ſay, vitiated and corrupted as hee is, to breath or ſpeake, than it is for all and euery one of them, euery way and euery day to ſin. On the other ſide, God is a God, with whom there can dwell no manner of wickednes, yea whoſe eies can at no hand behold that which is euill, whether it bee in deuiſe, or deſire, in thought, in word, or in deede. As ſoone ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13384:20"/>as man hath ſinned any manner of waye, ſo ſoone hath hee plunged himſelfe, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Gods abſolute and exact iuſtice, into moſt grieuous and fearefull iudgements. And though God ſtrike not preſently therefore (as wee ſee many times, according to his nature inclinable to mercie, yea mercie it ſelfe, hee doth with much patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and lenitie forbeare) wee muſt not thinke as the wicked doe, that either he doth it not, becauſe he cannot, (for what is it that hee cannot accompliſh?) or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee careth not for the ſins of our ſoules, for wee know that hee hateth ſinnes, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to, but rather to expreſſe the wonderfull ouerflowing mercie that is in him, waiting for mens conuerſion if it may be, yea aſſaying to worke it by all good meanes poſsible, or elſe that forbearing them, and they not amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he way the more ſharply and ſeuerely in his iuſtice puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for abuſing of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and turning his grace into wantonnes, as the Apoſtle ſaith. Which thing the world either not ſoundly knowing, or elſe not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely confeſsing the ſame to bee true, falleth into fearefull, dangerous, yea deadly extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: ſometimes accuſing God of iniuſtice, as as that either he ſtriketh them without cauſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13384:21"/>or more than by reaſon of the offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they haue deſerued: ſometimes they poſt the cauſe of their puniſhment, from them ſelues to others, ſuppoſing that other mens ſinnes rather than their owne, haue thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the Lord: and ſometimes againe, they aſcribe or attribute all to ſecondary cauſes, as to ſuch a coniunction and influence, of ſuch and ſuch planets, to the negligence or reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes of ſuch and ſuch perſons, to the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and power of ſuch and ſuch windes and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp;c. And ſometimes they doe prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge and accuſe their miſerable miſhap or fortune, as they call it, making her with the heathen a God, or goddeſſe: and ſometimes they fling out into one corruption, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to another. By meanes whereof, they as much as in them lyeth, rob God of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, as though there were any thing that without him or againſt him did beare ſway in the worlde, and ſpoile him of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as though that he, which indeede is the onely iuſt iudge of the worlde, could doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice or wrong, and forget his long forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hande: and ſo beſides that they depriue him of his honour in thankfulnes, profite not therby to amendment, &amp; make other things,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13384:21"/>namely creatures, God, &amp; a creator as it were, yea ſometimes ſuch things as neuer were in the nature of things, but in mans imagination and conceite onely, and hinder themſelues, &amp; it may be others likewiſe, by their bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alſo, from the ſight and ſenſe of ſinne, yea from religious repentance, and godly ſorrow for the ſame, whereby they might be led vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to amendment of life, not to bee repented of, and plunge themſelues into innumerable paines of bodie and ſoule here, and without ſpeciall fauour and grace of forgiuenes from God (who onely forgiueth ſinnes) into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rs in the world to come. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Gods children are ſo far off from entering into theſe corrupted courſes, that many times before iudgements, I will not ſay haue ſeazed vpon them, but euen before they haue beene threatned againſt them, haue yet in the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend feare which they haue had in their harts of them, either humbled themſelues, and as we may ſay, preuented the pouring foorth of Gods wrath vpon them: or elſe at the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering out of the ſame, or the firſt ſtroake thereof laide vpon them, haue ſoundly and ſpeedily caſt downe themſelues at the feete of Gods mercie, in faith vnfained, and ſincere
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13384:22"/>repentance, &amp; ſo if not remoued the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary or outwarde puniſhment (and yet vpon their ſubmiſsion, God hath been pleaſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, graciouſly to graunt the ſame) haue notwithſtanding found fauor from the Lord to vndergoe it for the preſent with patience and prayer, and ſincerely to profite by it (yea indeed to ouercome it) to Chriſtian mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and holy obedience.</p>
            <p>As for the ends, why God ſhould ſtrike vs, we muſt know and beleeue, that it is impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they ſhould be (whether wee reſpect them in themſelues, or as they proceed from him that is onely good) of any other nature than hee is. For as all his affections and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are meerely and abſolutely good, ſo muſt alſo all his purpoſes, and the ends that he ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth at be likewiſe, though alwaies happilie by reaſon of Satans malice and mans corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they bring not forth this effect in man. To make this plaine by ſome particulars. His loue is abſolutelie good, and no man that knoweth what either GOD or nature meaneth, can deny it: for if the loue of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creatures, as of parentes to children, huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes to wiues, friendes to friends, &amp;c. bee good and lawfull, then that which is in and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13384:22"/>from the diuine maieſtie muſt much more be ſo, becauſe it is more certaine, more holy, and indeed infinite, he hauing it alſo in himſelfe, and of himſelfe abſolutely &amp; perfectly good, whereas others haue it but by communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that in meaſure, and in men much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated and corrupted thorow the taint of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne. And yet this ſo excellently and abſolutely good, he laboureth to manifeſt, as in the correction of all men generally, ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of his owne people and children, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which the ſpirite ſaith, in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Hebrewes. <hi>My ſonne deſpiſe not the chastening of the Lorde, neither faint when thou art rebuked of him, for whome the Lord loueth he chaſtiſeth, and hee ſcourgeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſonne that he receiueth: And if we bee without correction whereof all are partakers, than are we baſtards, and not ſons and dauhg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Wherefore ſith in this and ſuch like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hee aimeth at the manifeſtation of his loue, and that is indeede the principall end of his chaſtiſements, ſpecially as in regard of his owne people, it cannot be but good. True it is that fleſh and bloud ſeeth not this, nor thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo. The reaſon is, becauſe their eyes are blind, and their vnderſtandings darke. But as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13384:23"/>it is not reaſon, becauſe a blinde man behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the Sunne, to conclude, there is no Sunne: ſo is it abſurd to ſay, becauſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked worldlings, neither feele nor feare theſe things, therefore they are not. For theſe are as all the reſt of the things of God, ſpecially as in reſpect of his purpoſe &amp; end, ſpirituall, and therefore muſt bee ſpiritually diſcerned: but they are carnall, and ſold vnder ſinne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in as much as ſince the deprauation &amp; corrupting of Gods image, wee are nothing els but both in bodie and ſoule tainted with all manner of euill: and ſith that euen ſince our regeneration and new birth, wee carrie about with vs (ſo long as wee dwell in theſe houſes of clay, and earthly tabernacles) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and remainders of ſinne: and we know by the light of the word, euery where almoſt reuealing it, and by the ſtinging teſtimony of our owne heart (which euen telleth it vs eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day that wee riſe vp, and euery night that we lye down) that ſinne diſpleaſeth his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed maieſtie, and God hath appointed puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and corrections, both outward &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, as one ſpeciall meane to repreſſe the rage and power of euill in vs, whileſt it ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from vs the droſſe of our corruption,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13384:23"/>and ſo mortifying in ſome meaſure ſinne in vs, faſhioneth vs the better and more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnto ſanctification (for this wee may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues of, that the decay of the one, is the increaſe of the other) we may euen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſee, as if it were in a moſt cleere and liuely looking glaſſe, that he aimeth at in theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, which he hath ſealed, not onely his owne glorie, but our good, both temporall and eternal, in this work of fatherly chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affliction. And this ſure cannot chuſe but be good alſo, howſoeuer ſomtimes by reaſon of the thicke clowde of our owne corruption, interpoſed between Gods works and our reformed iudgement, wee cannot ſo ſenſibly ſee, or ſo plainly perceiue the ſame, as we would or ſhould. Neither is this al, the bettering of vs in this life, but for as much as our good eſtate here, is in the purpoſe and councell of God, yet through his owne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace onely, infinitely as I may ſay, to be bettered in the life that is to come, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions doe not only frame vs to obedience in this world, but in ſome ſort pledge vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the ſaluation of our ſoules in eternall bleſſednes, according to which the Apoſtle affirmeth: <hi>We are chastened of the Lorde in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13384:24"/>this world, that wee ſhould not periſh with the wicked in that which is to come.</hi> And againe the ſpirit in another place ſayth: <hi>By many tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations we muſt enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Men by all this ſhould be perſwaded, of the holy purpoſes &amp; bleſſed ends of Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, and earneſtly labour by theſe (ſith God alſo himſelfe is pleaſed by them, to aime at that end, and to effect that grace in vs) to be out of loue and liking with this preſent euill world, and all the vanities and delights of the ſame, vſing it and them no further, than as by it and them we may be furthered in more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent graces, and to hunger and thirſt after that eternal felicitie, that is laid vp in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens for all thoſe, that in faith, patience, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and other good works, looke for and long after his bleſſed appearing.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what God mindeth to effect by ſtriking vs: but whether theſe fruites fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let our own practiſe declare. We are ſo far off from taking theſe things as pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his loue, that the more he layeth vpon vs that way, the more we thinke he hateth vs. And the reaſon is, becauſe we meaſure theſe matters, not by the line or elne of reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or religious reaſon, but by our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13384:24"/>much corrupted &amp; defaced, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that integritie which it had in creation. And then how can we in that darkenes ſee light, ſeeing that hindereth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beholding graces more cleere than theſe, that are to be ſeene in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corrections? And if wee cannot ſee in them his loue, till the thicke ſcales of our ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be pulled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eies of our minds, and vnderſtanding, howe ſhall wee perceiue that he aſſayeth our good therem, til the ſame alſo be remoued and taken away? For as we are hardly perſwaded of this, that ſtrokes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the fauor of him that ſoundly &amp; round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly layeth them vpon vs: ſo ſhall fleſh &amp; bloud neuer yeelde to this, that blowes better vs, till the hearte ſpecially inlightned beleeue the ſame, and wee know either by experience in our ſelues, or by obſeruation in others, that they haue not by nature, but by grace, gained that glorious iſſue. The like may wee ſay of pledging vp vnto vs the hope of heauen. For what man, if hee haue not more in him than man, will imagine that ſo harde a meaſure of afflictions and ſorrowes, as lie not onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the backs, but are in the ſoules of men, yea godly men, ſhould teſtifie vnto them ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces? wee rather ſay and ſee, that the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13384:25"/>father that beateth the child much and often, hardly mindeth to giue him the inheritance, and to make him Lord and heire of all. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Gods word telleth vs, that it is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with Gods elect: for if wee ſuffer with Chriſt, wee ſhall raigne with him, and being made conformable vnto him in his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wee ſhall alſo bee like him in glory, wee knowing that the momentany and light affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of this life, doe cauſe vnto vs, or bring with them a farre moſt excellent and eternall waight of glory. Nowe whether in theſe points it be better for vs, to beleeue God and his holy worde, or to truſt our owne reaſon, and humane iudgement, I had almoſt ſaid, let all the world iudge, but let the godly eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeake their mindes, and deliuer their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according to truth and right.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer hitherto hath beene deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, concerneth eſpecially, either the narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe, and the thing done as we ſay, or els ſome profitable pointes ariſing therefrom, or appertaining thereto. All which no doubt of it, are profitable, if they bee laide to heart, to build vs vp in knowledge and iudgement. But there is another thing beſides, that as in all cauſes generally, ſo particularly in this, wee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13384:25"/>muſt carefully labour to attaine to: and that is conſcience of the things that wee know, &amp; care to profite by them, to the bettering of vs in this life before God and man, and in our owne hearts alſo, that ſo in the comfortable feeling of it, we may haue aſſurance of hope and heart, that we ſhall not be confounded in that which is to come. And to this we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come or bee brought, but by making ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall vſe of and particular applying vnto our owne ſoules, the points of inſtruction, or the ſeuerall and ſundrie actions that God doth for, or amongſt the ſonnes of men. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which indeed, as in the publike miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, all paines taken is but labour loſt, and as it were wordes ſpoken in the aire, as the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of former ages, and the experience of our owne times, doe but too ſufficiently ſhewe: ſo in al priuate doctrines or documents, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be deliuered by the audible voice of man, or propounded vnto vs by the workes of God, in his mercie towards his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or in his iudgements towardes the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, will bee at the moſt, but as a wonder of nine daies, as we ſay in the Prouerbe, and like vnto water ſpilt vpon the ground. True it is, and I am ſure euery good man will confeſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13384:26"/>it, that neither the one nor the other, can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, either do vs good in this life, or further vs vnto eternall ſaluation (to make vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe and defence before God, and in our ſelues, I denye not, but ſome power they haue) otherwiſe than as they are ſanctified, by the almightie working of the bleſſed ſpirite. And therefore, when, or where, or howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God dealeth with vs, we ſhould preſently and vnfainedly humble our ſelues in prayer, and call and craue for grace to profit thereby. Howbeit though that I meane the gracious worke of Gods ſpirit in our hearts, be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall meane of our ſpirituall profiting, yet neither is it the only, neither indeed doth it fol low thereupon, that the others aboue recited, ſhould be reiected or refuſed. For euen as in our naturall life, the firſt and chiefe cauſe of all is God himſelfe, who as he giueth it vs, ſo vpholdeth it and maintaineth it, according to his good wil, that being here true that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>In him we liue, we moue, &amp; haue our being:</hi> and yet no man ſo vnwiſe as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe meate, drinke, cloth, ſleepe, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary helps and aides that way, for that were to tempt God, and to liue (if ſome one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could doe it) rather a miraculous than a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13384:26"/>naturall life, ſo in our ſpirituall life, though God by his holy ſpirite worke all in all, in the hearts of them that he hath marked out vnto eternall bleſſednes, yet no man that feareth God, or careth for his owne ſaluation, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecteth, much leſſe deſpiſeth the worde, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, prayer, admonitions, exhortations, rebukes, publike, priuate, &amp;c. but more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully frequenteth, and more religiouſly vſeth the ſame, and laboureth more to treaſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in his heart for goodnes, than hee doth all or any of the outward things appertaining to the body or naturall man. And euen ſo is it in this caſe, of applying to our purpoſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vſe in our ſoules of the waies and works of God, generall or particular, open or ſecret. To that therefore wee come, as indeed vnto the life and ſoule of the other thinges before going, and therein direct our ſpeech, as firſt to the whole land generally, who vpon euery ſuch particular occaſion ſhould make ſpeciall profite, as well becauſe all the ſeuerall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in a kingdome, or in a Church, make but one politicall or eccleſiaſticall bodie, and therefore if one ſuffer, all ſhould ſuffer, and if one reioyce, all ſhould do likewiſe, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome in Gods purpoſe and iudgement
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13384:27"/>are ſtriken, that all or many others, at the leaſt might amende, becauſe all haue ſinued and gone aſtraye, and ſtand in neede of the grace of God. And this is that ſurely that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our meaneth, when in the Goſpell hee ſaith, were thoſe Galileans, whoſe bloud <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their ſacrifices, greater ſinners than all the other? I tell you nay, but except ye amend your liues, ye ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: ſo ſecondly to the particular perſons, and places touched &amp; afflicted with this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſearefull iudgement, who if others, then they much more, ſhoulde vnfainedly ſtoope downe, and hartily and haſtily alſo humble themſelues, vnder the hand that hath ſtriken them, by how much not only in their own knowledge and conſcience, their ſinnes are greater than other mens, but alſo becauſe the puniſhment was preſent in their eies, fell vpon their bodies, goodes, and houſes, and ſhoulde (which whether it doth yea or no I know not, but if it do not, I pray God it may) more effectually therefore pearce and enter into their ſoules and ſpirites, for all time, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to come. What a mightie hande of God hath gone forth againſt the whole land, by manifold and fearefull fires in the ſeuerall
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13384:27"/>quarters and corners of it? which whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will but ſeriouſly thinke vpon them that are paſt, &amp; recall to memorie thoſe that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer men forget them, are yet freſh, and as it were bleeding in the harts and eies of them that feare God, hee caunot chuſe but ſee and confeſſe ſtrange and wonderfull iudgements. In ſome particulars behold the reſt: the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Beckles, the waſting of Nantwich, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming of Marleborough in the weſt, and which though it come in the laſt place is not the leaſt iudgement, the deſtroying of Stratforde vpon Auon twiſe in one yeare, with that great and grieuous puniſhment. Nay let vs proceede further, London the bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing beacon to the whole lande, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther citie of all the kingdome, hath bin made thorowe the iuſtice of God againſt it for ſin, a fearefull ſpectacle of Gods wrath to others, not onely while diuers priuate mens houſes, goodes and poſſeſsions haue beene defaced thereby, but while the ſteeple of their cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church (a place that many imagined for the deuotion and holines of it could not haue been touched with any ſuch iudgement) was not onely inflamed and conſumed it ſelfe, but miniſtred matter of feare alſo, and that not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13384:28"/>without good cauſe &amp; reſpect, that it would haue fired the whole citie it ſelfe. Sundrie other ſortes of iudgements hath God exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that famous place, and the whole lande withall, as with that infectiue and deſtroying ſickeneſſe the plague or peſtilence, that noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome diſeaſe of the ſmall pocks, meaſels, &amp;c. great penurie and ſcarſitie of victuals, and by meanes thereof and together with the ſame, a generall dearth of all thinges, belonging ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the pleaſures or the profits of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life: to which alſo adde the threatning of the ſworde for a fearefull inuaſion, and the feare of domeſticall ſtirres to diſturbe our long and happie peace, with infinit others, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the innumerable multitude of ſins and tranſgreſsious multiplied againſt his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, the very ſting whereof ſtandeth vp in our ſoules to accuſe vs euery night when we lye downe, and euery day when wee riſe vp. And yet who hath, I will not ſaye ſoundly profited by theſe things, for vnfained humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation before God, but thought ſeriouſly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for the bettering of vs, or for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good reſpect before men in the worlde. Certainely whoſoeuer will looke into theſe things with a ſingle eye, I doe not thinke the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13384:28"/>contrary, but hee ſhall clearely perceiue, that whatſoeuer iniquitie was in any particular perſon, ſtate, or degree amongſt vs, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer diſorder was either in church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, it reſteth notwithſtanding this hand of iuſtice and iudgement gone foorth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs ſtill vnreformed: as though wee thought that God in heauen did not either beholde our ſinnes, or did ſtrike vs without cauſe, or as though there were no ende why hee did puniſh vs. And though it bee true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, that in the midſt of theſe iudgements, he hath remembred mercie, and hath not let his wrath lie hard vpon vs, leſt we alſo might reach out our hands to iniquitie, but hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs great abundance of manifold fauours, turning our ſickenes into health, our penurie into plentie, our dread of danger and diſtreſſe into all manner of holy ioy, and ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides hath beſtowed vpon vs the bleſſed light of his holy worde both in the publike mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie &amp; priuate exerciſes of it, the very know ledge and light of it breaking foorth as the flowings of the ſea, if wee could ſo haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of it: and all this hath beene done to this end, that we might haue beene led by the lines of loue, and cordes of men, to haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13384:29"/>more vprightly and carefully with the Lord; who is the God of our life, and of our health, and of our peace and all: yet haue we miſled by the malice of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thorow the corruption of our owne hearts, and deceiued by the pleaſures of ſinne, which indure but for a while, lift vp our heeles and our handes againſt him, and hardned our hearts and our faces againſt all his waies, in all his workes, either of mercie or of iudgement, for he that was filthie, is filthie ſtill, and all the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the land (vnder the burden whereof alſo the very earth it ſelfe groaneth, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men ſhould much more mourne, if they were not ſenſeles and graceles) are ſo farre off from being leſſened and diminiſhed, that they daily increaſe and get head amongſt vs and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, which whoſoeuer wil but in vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart and iudgement, in the particulars conſider of, cannot but giue glory vnto God, and herein acknowledge and confeſſe the trueth. As for the pride of the lande, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, not onely by the exceſſe and abuſe of our commodities at home, but by bringing in of forraine wares, and olde and newe fond deuiſes, which in the finenes and in the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and vanitie of them, do ouer and beſides
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13384:29"/>waſt and weare the wealth of our own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, our golde, ſiluer, tinne, lead, and other things of worth and durablenes, being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported for ſuch trumperie. Gluttonie and drunkenneſſe, I thinke, did neuer ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, no not when England had the name for great hoſpitalitie and houſekeeping, there being come now in the ſteed of it, not onelie amongſt the poore, but amongſt the rich, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and all, either no houſekeeping at all, or the ſame ſo pinching and miſerable, as not onely the poore being readie to ſtarue in our ſtreetes, crie out of it, but euen the very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſeruants, many times doe very bitterlie, and that not without good cauſe, complaine of the ſame alſo.</p>
            <p>Touching the extortion, oppreſsion, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, vſurie and other iniquities that euery where amongſt high and low do daylie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, what ſhall we ſay, the very ſtones in the ſtreete, and the beaſtes in the fielde, and other dumbe and inſenſible creatures, though men ſhould hold their tongues, doe in their kinde, ſeriouſlie crie out againſt it and ſaye, euen as the Prophet did in his dayes, Iuſtice is turned into gall and wormewood, and the poore are bought and ſolde for ſiluer, and the needy for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13384:30"/>ſhooes: whoredome and filthie life, in al ſorts and degrees of men, both openly and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, did neuer ſo much ouer flow and increaſe as at this day. The ciuill Magiſtrate ſaith, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath no law to puniſh it, or correcteth it at the moſt with a ſimple whipping: and as for thoſe that haue the eccleſiaſticall cenſures in their hands, they ſurely haue no will to do it, but vſe their authoritie rather to picke mens purſes, than to inſtruct their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to conuert men vnto God. Yea, I wiſh with al my heart, that euen the very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters themſelues, to whom for ought I ſee, there is no other thing left to repreſſe euil by, than crying out againſt iniquity, were not in this as in other matters of as great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence tongue-tied and mute, or elſe as the prophet ſaith in another place, that they were light and wicked perſons, and had polluted the ſanctuarie, and wreſted the lawe. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe all tranſgreſsions in the ſeuerall ſortes and particularities of them, would be too lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and tedious, take one therefore, and the ſame as the moſt common, ſo the moſt grieuous, that by it we may iudge alſo of the reſt: the prophanation of the Sabbath is the ſin that I meane. Where is the man, woman, or child,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13384:30"/>that hath care and conſcience publikely to ſanctifie it, either by reuerent and religious preparing of themſelues to come to publike aſſemblies as they ſhould, or to repayre thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duetifullie as they ought, or to carrie themſelues there as beſeemeth ſuch heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes of prayer, preaching, &amp;c. What houſehoulder, man or woman, what childe, what ſeruant hath any regard priuately to ſpend it well in meditation and conference of things publikely taught them, in ſinging of pſalmes, in prayer, in thinking ſeriouſly vpon the creatures, in viſiting the ſicke, in dooing the workes of charitie and chriſtian loue? Or rather who prophaneth it not in publike, and in priuate, by themſelues and in company and in euery place almoſt: ſome by thinking it to be a day of bodily reſt only, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue themſelues and theirs ouer to ſleepe more and longer then, than on other dayes beſides: other ſome making no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the holy aſſemblies of the church, and religious exerciſes therein, than of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and common meetings, nor ſo much many times, and receiuing the word with no more reuerence &amp; attention than a prophane tayle, other ſome ſitting idle at their doores,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13384:31"/>gaping and gazing, ſuffering, yea ſome times commaunding their ſeruants and children to abuſe it, by dicing, daunſing, carding, ſtoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball playing, and other vnlawfull and wicked recreations: others alſo poaſting ouer their worldly affayres, as matters of accountes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring to Iuſtices for execution of law, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and intertaining their friendes, and ſuch other worldly things, to that daye, with a thouſand ſuch like abominations, fearefully committed and performed vpon that daye, that of all others ſhould bee beſt ſpent. For theſe may not wee ſaye, as the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in caſes of meaner importance: Shall not the land tremble for this, and euery one mourne that dwelleth therein? Or as another Prophet ſpeaketh againſt the people that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iaakob,</hi> for their pride, contempt of Gods word; and other iniquities, <hi>Aram</hi> before, and the Philiſtines behinde, and they ſhall deuoure Iſrael with open mouth, and yet for all this his wrath is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill: and good reaſon, for the people turneth not vnto him that ſtriketh them iuſtly for their ſinnes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they ſeeke the Lord of hoſtes: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will the Lord cut off from Iſrael, head
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13384:31"/>and tayle, branch and bodie in one day. The auncient and the honorable man hee is the head, and the Prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tayle, with many ſuch other things as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in that ninth chapter of <hi>Iſatah,</hi> which I would deſire the godly reader, with care to looke vpon, and in conſcience to make vſe of. For who knoweth whether this bee yet, the day of Gods grace offered, and the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time if it be receiued? Or who can tell whether this bee not a foretelling and a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running ſigne alſo, that the land may (and that or euer it be long, for ought we know) bee conſumed with fire from the Weſt, by the Turke, Pope, Spaniard, &amp; other inſtruments of Gods wrath to puniſh a ſinfull and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nation: All which would bee glad, not only for the inlarging of their territories and kingdomes, but euen of hatred more than cruell, and bloodie againſt vs to whet their teeth vpon our bodies and bones, and to bath their ſwords in our blood: or elſe who can or dare ſay, that this may not be an aſſured teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, that the Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhortly come in the cloudes, in a melting and conſuming fire going before him, and deſtroying all things, with great power and glory to iudge
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13384:32"/>the quick and the dead? Sin not at the height it is at, doth in full prouoke the one, &amp; with earneſtnes calleth for our aduerſaries to come out againſt vs in troopes and armies, and on the other ſide all ſignes (if I be not deceiued) that ſhould goe before that great and terrible daye of the Lorde bee accompliſhed already. Sith things then are ſo vncertaine, that wee knowe not when nor where, nor how the Lord will come vpon vs, and yet wee cannot but feare that hee is nigh, euen at the doore, why ſhould wee deferre with the wicked, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen therein, or thereby, cauſing the Lordes wrath to breake forth againſt vs to our vtter confuſion: or rather conſidering that all theſe things muſt bee diſſolued, why doe wee not make this vſe of it, to learne what manner of people wee ſhould bee in holy conuerſation and godly life, looking for, &amp; haſtning vnto the comming of that day of the Lord, by the which the very heauens being on fire, ſhall be diſſolued, and the elements ſhall melt with heate? But who (I wil not ſay practiſeth theſe things, for the number of ſuch perſons is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as rare in the world, as a blacke ſwanne amongſt foules) thinketh vpon theſe things ſeriouſly? Surely, ſurely, the moſt part buſie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13384:32"/>their mindes and their mouthes alſo farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: for ſome giue themſelues ouer to filthie and fooliſh ſpeech, which not onely bringeth no grace or godly edification to the hearer, but rather corrupteth good maners. Other ſome though they fall not ſo fouly, yet are ouertaken in their diſcourſes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of profit, hauking, hunting, merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, purchaſing landes, &amp;c. which though in themſelues they be not euill, yet becauſe they continually put better matter out of place, they are become the ſin of their ſoules. And if it ſo fall out, that now and then, they or ſome of them ſtumble vpon good things, be it either in word or deede, by the motion of their owne minde, or occaſion from others, it is certainely but as a flaſhe lightening, no man knoweth whence it commeth, nor whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it goeth, and euen vaniſheth away, as if it were in the firſt appearing of it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely thorow their ſins of ignorance, negligence, careleſnes, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt &amp; prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it is likely that vengeance ſhall breake forth from the Lord in a grieuous both mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and manner, &amp; fearefully conſume both bough and branch, roote and bodie, trunke ſtocke, and all in a day.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13384:33"/>
            <p> And if this bee the ſtate and condition of the generalitie, as indeede it is, what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the particulars, the whole bodie conſiſting of them as it were of ſeueral parts, but that they alſo muſt remaine vnder the ſame iudgement? To you therefore that now are vnder this hand &amp; hammer of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie indignation is it that I write and ſpeake. Can you deny, but that euen many dayes and yeares alreadie paſſed, you haue long agoe pulled this and a more grieuous iudgement by much, downe vpon you from almightie God? If you ſhould, the heauens would bluſh at you, and the earth would beare witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and teſtifie vnto your faces, the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of your words and workes. Mee thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it ſhould bee farre better for you to giue glorie to God, and vnfeinedly confeſſe that it is his ſingular fauour to haue ſpared you ſo long, and that it is his more then common mercy, that ye were not al conſumed. What hath been threatned againſt you out of Gods word, you cannot be ignorant of. What pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments haue light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, by the plague, the ſmall pockes, and now this laſt fearefull fire, you cannot but feele. What? Hath God ſtricken you without a cauſe? Be it far from
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13384:33"/>you, either to ſpeake it or thinke it, for that were to condemne the moſt iuſt iudge of the world for your owne clearing, yea and to go againſt the ſtinging teſtimonie which euery day when you riſe vp, and euery night when you lye downe, telleth you the cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But if you ſhould proceede to that height, are not other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue watched ouer you, &amp; preached &amp; ſpoken vnto you in the name of the Lord, able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uince you of falſehood to your faces, and to throw the dounge of your iniquity vpon your countenances? Giue them therefore leaue to declare the truth to you, and labour to beare with patience, and to profit by the word of exhortation, ſith it is directed to you for your good, and vnfeined humiliation alſo: for they knowe you, and your offences far better than you your ſelues. Perhaps you will thinke this ſpeech ſtrange, but deceiue not your owne hearts, I beſeech you, for if you will weigh, that naturallie we are blinde to diſcerne ſinne, and after they ſee it, yet many times they are partiall in their owne waies, and euen bleare vp their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and harden their hearts, and againe that they are more quicke and better ſighted, to diſcerne other mens tranſgreſsions than
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13384:34"/>their owne: as alſo that God reuealeth not the ſinnes of the people vnto his faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the Prophets by the halfes, I think you would, or at the leaſt I am ſure you ſhould be of another mind. To reckon vp all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars were harde and impoſsible, for who can vnderſtande his faultes? And yet not to lay downe ſome, were to faile in the iuſtifify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the charge, which were vniuſt, and to let you alone in your iniquities, which ſhuld be vncharitable. This therefore I ſay, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the infinite and innumerable ſinnes of your ſoules, there are ſome particulars that haue beene and are moſt odious before God, and moſt apparant in the view of the world. Amongſt which I reckon in the firſt place a fearefull contempt of godlines in the moſt of you, and a great and grieuous careleſneſſe thereof euen in the beſt. How often and long hath God ſpoken vnto you, by the publike miniſterie of his worde, in the holy exerciſes of prayer, preaching, adminiſtration and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of his bleſſed ſacraments? If you could haue ſeene your happines in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, both for the length of them, &amp; the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the men that God vſed as meanes to publiſh his trueth vnto you, your fauors both
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13384:34"/>waies not farre inferior to any congregation of the land, and in theſe reſpects indeede go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before many it had beene well: but how little you haue profited by them, nay howe careleſly you haue heard them, &amp; how cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you haue frequented them, your groſſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the grounds of Chriſtian religion ſheweth the firſt, fewe or none of you being able to render a reaſon thereof, to them that ſhall aske you, &amp; your ſleeping in the church, talking one with another, and turning of your bookes there, and vſing of your owne priuate deuotions or prayers in the time of publike preaching &amp; prayer, a grieuous tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion no doubt proueth the ſecond: and your dayly and continuall abſence therfrom, and ſpecially vpon the Lordes day then lying in your beds, haunting of alehouſes, riding and going abroad for your worldly affaires of pleaſure and profite manifeſteth the third. And how weary you are when you are there let this teſtifie: none preuent the time of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblies, and ſome come in the midſt of your exerciſes, to the great diſturbance of the ſame, and others that are there: and that ſome againe before the ſermons are finiſhed, other ſome after the prayers made, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13384:35"/>the ſinging of the Pſalme, and the vſuall bleſsing to bee pronounced departe thence, wherof you as well as they that tarrie ſhould be partakers, poſting alſo out of the Church, as it were fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a play or may game, as though you ſuppoſed, that no more reuerence ſhould be ſhewed there than in other places, or that ſome parte of diuine ſeruice belonged vnto you and not other ſome, whereas in trueth you ought to be alike partakers of the whole. And how ſhould wee looke for any goodnes where this that is the ſeede of ſinne, and the nurſe of all abominations ſwayeth ſo much? Surely when men haue once caſt Gods lawe behind their backes, and haue it not in deede in a high and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d regard, what can there bee to reſtraine them from euill? or to direct them in good? Nay what ſhall not then bee right and lawfull, though indeede it bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo corrupt and vile. From this therfore, as from a ſtreame and fountaine of filthineſſe, haue flowed all your othes, particular tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, as firſt for example your ſwearing and curſing: by the firſt blaſpheming of Gods name, and haling down wrath and vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the Lord vpon your ſelues, your wiues, children, familie, friends, yea all the goodes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13384:35"/>and cattle that you haue and poſſeſſe, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine, and ſure wee are that the plague of God ſhal not depart from the houſe of the ſwearer: as alſo wee may perceiue by the ſigne of the flying booke mentioned Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. 5. in which were contained curſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euery one that ſweareth, who alſo ſhould be cut off as wel on this ſide, as on that: yea that this iudgement ſhould enter into, and remaine in the midſt of ſuch ſwerers houſes, and ſhould conſume the ſame with the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof, and ſtones thereof. And by the ſecond not onely teſtifying the malice and madnes of your owne harts, againſt men and other creatures of GOD, vpon which you powre out the poyſon of your mindes and mouthes, but drawing iniquitie with the cordes of vanitie, and ſinne as it were with cart ropes, that ſo that might bee fulfilled in you, that in the book of Pſalmes is ſpoken of the notorious wicked, As hee loued curſing, ſo ſhall it come vnto him, and as he loued not bleſsing ſo ſhall it be farre from him: and as hee clothed himſelfe with curſing like a ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo ſhall it come into his bowels like water, and like oyle into his bones. And by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13384:36"/>both of them defiling the aire aboue you, and polluting the earth beneath you, with the creatures thereupon, yea by your bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, infecting and corrupting your wiues, children, ſeruants, and all that haue any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation or acquaintance with you, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing to learne from you but that which is euill, will in the proneneſſe of their owne nature to naughtineſſe, eaſily treade in your bad ſteps, and much more eaſily reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you in corruption, than other men in goodnes, by how much you doe more nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtraightly by many waies touch them than others. And as for your owne idlenes, and the bad bringing vp of your youth and children, both ſonnes and daughters, it is pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to beholde, and I cannot without great griefe of heart, thinke or ſpeake of it: what a ſhame before men, nay indeede what ſinne is it before God, to ſee amongſt you day labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and men of manuall occupations (who according to Gods ordinance, and his iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vpon them for ſinne, ſhuld eat their bread in the ſweate of their browes, and get it as wee ſay with their fingers endes) haunt and frequent alehouſes, ſpending there not onely houres, but dayes, and in that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13384:36"/>the neglect of their callings, by which they ſhould maintaine themſelues and theirs, waſting that alſo which they haue gotten, &amp; ſhuld be as the reward of their honeſt labors, ſo the neceſſary and needfull reliefe of their wiues, children, and other at home, where they ſhould rather ſpend it in deede, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of mutuall comforte amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, than vpon the ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> and wicked and lewd perſons in thoſe houſes of vnthriftines, yea ſome of them of diſhoneſty? Now for your youth, is it not lamentable to ſee boies and girles, of tenne, twelue, yea a fourteene yeares of age, and many vnder theſe yeares alſo, to ſwarme in your ſtreetes, and to runne vp and downe daily in mire and dirt, both wearing out their ſhooes, and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their apparell, and that without laying their hands to any honeſt labours to get ſome thing towards their maintenance and reliefe? Yea and ſome of them I feare me that follow not this bad trade, worſe occupied by much, in pilfering, breaking of hedges, learning to lie, ſweare, and make no concſience of anie ſinne. And as for thoſe few that you ſeeme to put to learning, if you conſider the places whither they goe, the perſons to whome (I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13384:37"/>neede nor particularize this, for you knowe what I meane) and the ſmall profite they take thereby, it were almoſt as ſmall a tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God and men, to let them liue idly with the reſt, as to traine them vp in ſorte as they are. God hath graciouſly prouided far better for you, if you coulde either ſee it or haue care and conſcience to vſe it well. As for your ſelues, you haue long agoe done what you could to put religion from you, by offering not onely manifold vnkindneſſes to the perſons that offered it vnto you, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to the trueth it ſelfe, and yet though it be full ſore againſt your willes, it is by hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and others, and thoſe that loue you, and care for you more than your ſelues, vphelde ſtill. And now what goe you about, namely to baniſh learning from you and yours? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you will think it a hard charge, but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it appeareth not onely by this, that you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your ſchoolehouſe, the place appointed for the good bringing vp of your youth, to goe to foule decay, but haue no regarde at all in a manner that they might attaine to ſome good meaſure of knowledge in humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, what will bee the iſſue conſider: in a word. Contempt of the worde carieth with
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13384:37"/>it alwaies all maner of impietie: and lacke of knowledge, breedeth all barbarouſnes: and then what can you look for, but euen to haue that fulfilled in you, that the ſcripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of a rebellious and ſtifnecked people, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim ſhall eate vp Manaſſeh, and Manaſſeh Ephraim, and ſo you to become a ſauage and wilde people deuoid of pietie, charitie, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, righteouſneſſe, loue, &amp;c. and filled with all manner of vngodlines and ſinne, to which as ſeemeth to me by your crooked paths, you haue made more than poſt haſte already. And though God by many croſſes and loſſes laide vpon you and yours, labor to ſtay you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, and particularly hath plagued almoſt al of you, with great and grieuous pouertie, (more I am ſure than many of you will bee knowne of) ſo that (ſome few of you excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) you liue for the moſt part by ſhifting, if not vnhoneſt deuiſes and trades: yet you will not ſee the hand that ſtriketh you with beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie as it were, and contempt for your idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and careleſnes, and ſo turne vnto him, but ſhifting it from your ſelues vnto others, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly laye the fault vpon thoſe that in manie reſpects haue been but too bountifull and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial vnto you and yours. And yet I would
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13384:38"/>euen from the bottome of my heart, if GOD ſaw it ſo good, that your iniquitie and ſinne had ſtaied here, and had not proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But ſurely it is farre otherwiſe with you: for as the godly thorow the light of God his truth, and the powerful working of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirite, are mightilie caried from faith to faith, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one good work to an other, ſo are you in Satans malice againſt you, and the ſtrength of your owne corruption violently harried from one tranſgreſsion to another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, that ſo that may be true in you, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. The wicked muſt waxe worſe and worſe, and filling vp the meaſure of their tranſgreſsions, bee at the laſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with his moſt fearefull and iuſt iudgements. What ſhall I ſay of your exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue drinking, abuſing therein and therewith that and many other his good creatures, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you ſometimes for neceſsitie eſpecially, and ſome times for delight alſo, I confeſſe? yea, is it not written in many of your faces and foreheads, ſo that hee that regardeth but the rednes of your eyes, the heate of your countenances, the ſwelling of your vaines, and ſundry ſuch other outward ſignes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie, might with ſmall a doe poynte
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13384:38"/>and painte out, what manner of men you are, and as if it were with great capitall letters written in your foreheads, ſo as hee that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth may reade the ſame, ſee and behold bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and quaffing written therein? And yet herein is this your ſinne amongſt others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come exceedingly ſinfull, that many of you leaue your owne houſes, and go vp &amp; down to other places for ſtrong drinke and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and not contented therewith, you delight to drawe others from townes and places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and rounde about you, to be partakers with you of the ſelfe ſame iniquitie, and that not onely vpon your market and fayre daies, and times of reſort, but euen vpon other daies of the weeke, yea vpon the Lords day it ſelfe, wherein you are ſo farre off from withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euill, that not one of you yet for ought I knowe, hath been found either to repreſſe this foule vice of quaffing and drunkennes in your ſelues, or to ſhut your doores againſt them that fall into riot and exceſſe that way. Adde vnto theſe, the adulteries, whoredomes and fearefull filthineſſes that haue heretofore, and daylie doe fall out amongſt you, and then you ſhall ſee alſo, whether God haue cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſlie ſtricken you, with this and other iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13384:39"/>or whether you haue not indeede good cauſe for the ſame, vnfeinedly and ſpeedily to humble your ſelues leaſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the wrath begun, proceede and breake forth, to an vtter waſting of you and yours. For your ſecret ſinnes that way, I will ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but leaue them to God to whome they are beſt knowne, and to your owne hearts, which ſhould bee touched with a godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them, and for your other iniquities likewiſe. Conſider a little I pray you of your open tranſgreſsions, and waigh them for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life. Diuers of your daughters and maidſeruants, haue beene in former time and of late, ſhamefully defiled. Your ſonnes and other of your families, haue been the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and the actors of this grieuous villanie, wherein alſo ſundry of them haue growne to this ſhameleſneſſe in their ſinne, that they haue gone with out ſtretched necks, and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen foreheads, as though they had done none iniquitie at all. Your towne by this mernes too much impoueriſhed alreadie, hath beene charged with the keeping of a baſtardlye broode, beſide other foule inconueniences that haue followed &amp; flowen from this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tranſgreſsion. To reckon vp the reſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13384:39"/>of your iniquities would bee to too tedious, by theſe labour to learne, to loth, and to leaue them, and all the other whatſoeuer, &amp; ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpeedily to turne vnto the Lorde, and no doubt but you ſhall find fauor, for yet with the Lord there is mercie, that he may bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Otherwiſe, know and aſſure your ſelues, that if thorowe the pleaſures of ſinne which indure but for a while, your hearts ſhall bee hardened, and you either put the euill day farre from you, or do not with ſpeede turne vnto God, in a holy conuerſation and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, you and yours ſhall both feele the hande of God purſuing you in this life, and eternally periſh in that which is to come. Good and bad are this day propounded vnto you, and the way of life and death ſet before your eyes, Looke well to it, and beware that the Lord haue not iuſt occaſion thorow your careleſeſſe and contempt of his trueth, to ſay, Thy deſtructon, O Iſraell, is of thy ſelfe, I knowe that the waies and the workes of a mans life, are not in his owne hands or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but that it is God that worketh in vs, both the will and the deed according to his own good pleaſure. Notwithſtanding, ſith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene ſo gracious to offer, let not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:13384:40"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> leaſt otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> harde againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. And that which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me particular hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doe in the largenes of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeake and wiſh vnto the whole land, whoſe peace and proſperitie I will pray for &amp; to my utter moſt (God aſsiſting me) procure al the daies of my life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
